<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Earth raining vpon heauen A sermon preached at the assises holden at Nottingham, August 5. 1614. By VVilliam VVorship, Doctor in Diuinitie.</title>
            <author>Worship, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15721</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25994</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120299</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855498</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855498</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20993</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15721)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20993)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1125:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Earth raining vpon heauen A sermon preached at the assises holden at Nottingham, August 5. 1614. By VVilliam VVorship, Doctor in Diuinitie.</title>
                  <author>Worship, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Thomas Snodham] for Thomas Pauier, and are to be sould at his shop in Iuy-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20993:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20993:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Earth raining vpon Heauen.</hi> A SERMON PREACHED at the Aſsiſes holden at <hi>Nottingham, Auguſt</hi> 5. 1614. BY VVILLIAM VVORSHIP, Doctor in DIVINITIE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Panier,</hi> and are to be ſould at his ſhop in <hi>Iuy-Lane.</hi> 1614.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20993:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20993:2"/>
            <head>TO MY GOOD Friend, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Doctor <hi>Hall.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>YR: the combination of <hi>Zeale</hi> and <hi>Learning,</hi> wherewith <hi>GOD</hi> hath honoured you: together with your Loue, imparted kindly to mee by <hi>Letter,</hi> haue beene the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectiues to this <hi>ſmall Remembrance.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I couet to ſhew my <hi>Thankefulneſſe,</hi> and the <hi>great Reſpect</hi> I deſeruedly beare you. I know mine <hi>inſufficiencie</hi> to performe much on the beſt tearmes; much leſſe, at this time, being worne with <hi>tedious Sickeneſſe,</hi> by the meanes of a <hi>groſſe</hi> and <hi>cruell</hi> Ayre. Yet, it pleas'd the <hi>Lord</hi> to proſper this poore <hi>Indeauour</hi> at the <hi>Deliuerie;</hi> and who can tell, if hereafter <hi>Hee</hi> will bleſſe it, to the <hi>winning of ſome Soule?</hi> O, if <hi>Hee</hi> doe, what a ſweet Addition ſhall it be to his
<pb facs="tcp:20993:3"/> former mercies. This <hi>gracious GOD</hi> aſsiſt vs by his <hi>Spirit,</hi> incourage vs daily in the courſe of our <hi>Miniſterie;</hi> that ſpending our ſelues for the good of his <hi>Elect,</hi> wee may one day <hi>ſhine like Starres, for euer and euer.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your vnfayned Friend WILLIAM WORSHIP.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20993:3"/>
            <head>THE TEXT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>LVKE 7. 37. 38.</bibl>
                  <p>37 <hi>And behold, a Woman in the Citie, which was a ſinner, when ſhee knew that Jeſus ſate at Table in the Phariſes houſe, ſhee brought an Alabaſter-Boxe of Oyntment:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>38 <hi>And ſhee ſtood at his feete, behinde him, wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and began to waſh his feete with teares, and did wipe them with the hayres of her head, and kiſſed his feete, and annoynted them with the Oyntment.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr Sauiour <hi>Chriſt</hi> was invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a <hi>Phariſee</hi> to eate. Hee went. For meate and drinke? No: Yes: It was his <hi>meate</hi> and drinke <hi>to doe</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 4. 34.</note> 
               <hi>his Fathers will,</hi> to conuert
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20993:4"/> and comfort <hi>Sinners,</hi> as he doth in this <hi>Story.</hi> VVhere is a <hi>Watch-word [Behold,</hi>] and a <hi>Deuout Party,</hi> largely deſcrib'd: by her <hi>Sexe [a woman</hi>] by her <hi>Place [in the Citie,</hi>] by her <hi>Reputation, [a Sinner,</hi>] by her <hi>Faith, [when ſhee knew that Ieſus ſate at Table in the Phariſes houſe, Shee went to him,</hi>] by her <hi>liberall Intent, [ſhee brought an Alabaſter-Boxe of Oyntment,</hi>] by her <hi>Humilitie, [ſhe ſtood at his feete,</hi>] by her <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſlie, [behinde him,</hi>] by her <hi>godly Sorrow, [weeping,</hi>] by her <hi>Increaſe of that ſorrow [ſhe beganne to waſh his feete with her teares,</hi>] by the <hi>Neglect of her ſelfe, [and did wipe them with the hayres of her head</hi>] by her <hi>Loue [and kiſſed his feete,</hi>] by her <hi>Bountie, [and annoynted them with the Oyntment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus am I imbarqued for a long Voyage, and am to paſſe the <hi>Magellan Straits:</hi> but my comfort is, I ſaile in the <hi>DESIRE,</hi> where the <hi>Word</hi> is my <hi>Compaſſe,</hi> and the <hi>Lord</hi> my <hi>Pilot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>[<hi>Behold.</hi>] This particle, <hi>Behold,</hi> is ſometime in Scripture <hi>Repletiue,</hi> but in this place <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtratiue,</hi> importing <hi>Attention</hi> and <hi>Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:20993:4"/> The <hi>People</hi> muſt at one time attend two <hi>Preachers;</hi> the <hi>Man</hi> in the black gowne, that deliuers the Meditations of his heart, and the mighty GOD, whoſe Chaire and Pulpit is in Heauen. About the Heart (ſaith<note place="margin">De Re Anat. lib. 7. c. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Columbus</hi>) are two Eares, a Right one, and a Left, both thin-skin'd, and anfractuous: whoſe vſe, in <hi>Reaſon,</hi> is to preſerue the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi> and <hi>Arteriall</hi> veynes from burſting; in <hi>Diuinitie,</hi> to teach vs to draw vp our Hearts to our Eares, that the word may pearce both at once. The end of all our Senſes, is to bring vs to <hi>Christ,</hi> but of <hi>Hearing</hi> chiefly, as being the ſence of <hi>Diſcipline.</hi> The Goſpell for the eare, the eare for the Goſpell, and both for the <hi>Conſcience.</hi> So that to <hi>attend,</hi> is to <hi>heare, meditate, practiſe.</hi> For as <hi>Art</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Nature</hi> is lame, <hi>Nature</hi> without <hi>Art,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plut. Mor. 1.</note> blinde, and both without <hi>Experience</hi> fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe: ſo <hi>Hearing</hi> without <hi>Meditation,</hi> is win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, <hi>Meditation</hi> without <hi>Hearing</hi> erroneous, and both without <hi>practiſe,</hi> vneffectuall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beloued,</hi> not <hi>I,</hi> but th'<hi>Evangeliſt,</hi> not <hi>He,</hi> but GOD inioynes you to attend: if I thought
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20993:5"/> you would not, I would call vpon the dead <hi>Element</hi> to hearken, and crie out with the Prophet <hi>Ieremie, O Earth, Earth, Earth, heare</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 22. 19.</note> 
               <hi>the word of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Further, this, <hi>Behold,</hi> implyeth Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Things are wondered at, eyther for their <hi>greatnes,</hi> or <hi>rarenes:</hi> both theſe are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous in this Example. Beholde <hi>an huge Whale,</hi> a <hi>liuing Mountayne of ſinne,</hi> a <hi>mightie Sea-monster</hi> caught in the ſilly Draw-net of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> and the Cords vnbroke, and the <hi>Maſhes</hi> whole, becauſe the <hi>Fiſhers</hi> name is VVONDERFVLL. Behold a <hi>Blacke-Moore</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſaiah. 9. 6.</note> waſht white, a <hi>Leopard</hi> made ſpotles, a merry <hi>Larke</hi> turn'd to a groning <hi>Culuer:</hi> Behold a modeſt boldnes, a ioyfull ſadnes, an acting paſſion, a ſpeaking ſilence. Behold <hi>one weeping.</hi> Is't ſuch a matter to ſee one weepe? A great matter to ſee one weepe for ſinne. This of the <hi>Watch-word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Devout Partie</hi> followeth, who is firſt deſcribed by her <hi>Sexe [a woman.</hi>] If you aske <hi>What woman? Auſten, Gregory, Beda,</hi> tell you <hi>Mary Magdalen:</hi> others doubt: heere godly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20993:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Ignorance</hi> is ſafeſt. The Lord, for iuſt cauſes<note place="margin">Matth. 15.</note> hath concealed her <hi>Name,</hi> as he did the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro-Phaenicians,</hi> her <hi>Parallel.</hi> Suffice it vs, that a <hi>woman</hi> muſt reade vs a Lecture of <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi> Doe wee ſcorne it? But <hi>Apollos</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd not to be <hi>Catechiz'd</hi> by a <hi>woman,</hi> and<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Super Cant. Ser.</hi> 75. Ierem. 8. 7. Prouer. 6. 6.</note> 
               <hi>women</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>) were at <hi>Christs Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, The Apostles of the Apostles.</hi> As proud as we are, we are ſent to the <hi>Crane,</hi> and <hi>Swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi> for Inſtruction, and (by your leaues) to that little, leane, creeping <hi>Thing, the Piſmire.</hi> VVhat beauteous floure, what medicinall hearb, but may be found in the <hi>Womans gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den?</hi> May we not learne <hi>Meekneſſe</hi> of <hi>Sarah, Fortitude</hi> of <hi>Deborah, Patience</hi> of <hi>Naomi, Humbleneſſe</hi> of <hi>Hanna, Wiſedome</hi> of <hi>Abigail, Zeale</hi> of <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and all theſe <hi>Graces</hi> of the <hi>Virgin Mary?</hi> O that our <hi>women</hi> would tread in theſe ſteppes! No: they will not, they care not, they degenerate, they goe like <hi>men;</hi> and ſome feare they will ſhortly ride after that ill-fauour'd faſhion, vs'd in this <hi>Realme,</hi> before <hi>Richard</hi> the ſeconds <hi>Queene</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Annals of England.</note> came from <hi>Bohemia.</hi> Harke, yee <hi>Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20993:6"/> Hic mulier,</hi> ere long, will be good La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin. VVell, ſince they will not few by thoſe <hi>Samples,</hi> I will ſend them <hi>Latimers Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerchers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 16. 23.</note> and worke <hi>woes</hi> in <hi>Chayne-stitch,</hi> as the Prophet <hi>Ezechiell</hi> hath taught me.</p>
            <p>The ſecond branch, is this good <hi>womans Place of abode.</hi> She was a <hi>Citizen.</hi> Of what Citie? Some ſay <hi>Nain,</hi> ſome <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> we cannot point downe on any one. It is like her worſt ſtaynes were <hi>Citie-ſinnes,</hi> for, the <hi>Country</hi> (vſually) ſinnes more bungerly than <hi>Corporations.</hi> Mightineſſe of ſtate, frequencie of ſtrangers, multitude of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, curiouſneſſe of Arts, heapes of riches, ſumptuouſneſſe of buildings, ſtore of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion, ſtrength of munition, make <hi>Cities</hi> ſettle vpon their <hi>Lees;</hi> and yet not they, but their <hi>abuſe. O harlot Ieruſalem! O bloudy Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niueh!</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 16. 33. Nahum 3. 1.</note> they be the words of the Prophet <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zechiel,</hi> and <hi>Nahum. Diana</hi> at <hi>Epheſus, Lais</hi> at <hi>Corinth, Mahumet</hi> at <hi>Constantinople, Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> at <hi>Venice</hi> nothing but <hi>Pride,</hi> becauſe <hi>Venice</hi> is nothing but <hi>Riches,</hi> but at <hi>London, Omnia benè.</hi> Farre be it from mee
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20993:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> to be blowne vp with ſuch a <hi>Gunne-pouder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeale,</hi> as to forget the <hi>honour</hi> of that <hi>Place:</hi> yet this I muſt tell them, that as <hi>the great ſickeneſſe,</hi> ſo the <hi>great ſinnes,</hi> ordinarily, are from them deriued to the <hi>Countrey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Reputation</hi> of this <hi>woman</hi> comes next to be ſcanned. She was counted <hi>mercenary,</hi> a notorious ſinner, a <hi>whipster.</hi> Yet, loe, <hi>ſhee</hi> is now become an <hi>honest woman.</hi> Vpbraid her not then with her former lewdneſſe, but giue <hi>God</hi> thankes for her preſent goodneſſe. The Lord hath forgot, &amp; ſhall we remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber? The <hi>Angells</hi> reioyce, and ſhall wee be fullen? A graceleſſe <hi>woman</hi> (ſaith a <hi>Father</hi>)<note place="margin">Ambroſ.</note> that had long in ſnared a young <hi>man,</hi> now conuerted, ſpeakes to him familiarly, as he goes by. He regardes her not. She replies, <hi>Ego ſum;</hi> Its I. He anſwers, <hi>At ego non ſum ego, But I am not my ſelfe: I am not as I was, I was not as I am.</hi> There were ſome of the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, Idolaters, Adulterers,</hi> and (which I tremble to vtter) <hi>Buggerers:</hi> and yet they<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 11.</note> were <hi>waſhed,</hi> yet they were <hi>ſanctified,</hi> yet<note place="margin">In feſt. Mar. Magdal.</note> they were <hi>iustified. VVho would deſpaire</hi> (ſaith
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20993:7"/> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi>) when ſuch great <hi>ſinners obtayne not mercy</hi> onely, but <hi>glory?</hi> Did not <hi>Rahab,</hi> the <hi>Harlot,</hi> recouer her ſelfe? I dare ſay more, (and S. <hi>Matthew</hi> will beare me out) <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe deſcended from her, and from <hi>Thamar</hi> too: to ſuccour <hi>ignoble birth,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chriſoſtome,</hi> to comfort <hi>diſtreſſed ſoules,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ierome.</hi> Here let vs pauſe, and ſigh,<note place="margin">In Math.</note> and ioy: ſigh at our ſinnes, ioy at the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drous loue of our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> who for our ſakes became a <hi>worme,</hi> and no <hi>man,</hi> the very<note place="margin">Pſal. 22. 6.</note> 
               <hi>ſcorne of men,</hi> and <hi>contempt</hi> of the <hi>People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let vs now weigh this <hi>womans Faith,</hi> ſo highly commended afterward by our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour.</hi> Thus ſhee reaſons: <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daines not to eate with the <hi>Phariſes,</hi> (to whom, of his goodneſſe, hee preferres vs <hi>Harlots,) therefore</hi> will I to him, and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune him for <hi>mercy.</hi> I know theſe haughtie <hi>Sectaries</hi> will mocke mee, and all the <hi>Towne</hi> and <hi>Country</hi> will ring of mee; but I am ſo ſicke of <hi>Sinne,</hi> and feele ſuch <hi>Convulſions,</hi> that I dye, alas, vnleſſe I repayre to him. And in truth, <hi>ſhee</hi> had periſhed, had <hi>ſhe</hi> not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20993:7"/> imbrac'd him: for, no other <hi>Name</hi> was<note place="margin">Acts 4. 12.</note> there vnder <hi>Heauen,</hi> by which <hi>ſhee</hi> could poſſibly be ſaued. If a <hi>King</hi> be diſpleas'd, (though his <hi>Wrath</hi> be like the <hi>Roaring of a</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 19. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Lyon</hi>) yet, <hi>Force</hi> may encounter him, or <hi>Friends</hi> intreate him, or <hi>Muſicke</hi> ſtill him, or <hi>Eloquence</hi> perſwade him, or <hi>Promiſes</hi> winne him, or <hi>Riches</hi> tempt him, or <hi>ſomething</hi> preuayle with him: but when <hi>fire</hi> is kindled in the wrath of <hi>The Lord of Hoſts,</hi> that conſumes the <hi>Earth,</hi> and burnes vnto the bottome of <hi>Hell,</hi> what <hi>Creature</hi> dare ſtep forth to looke him in the face, much leſſe to parle with him, and leaſt of all, to grap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with him? Dare Man? Like enough; for hee is a <hi>proud Worme,</hi> and will lift vp his <hi>Neb,</hi> but the <hi>Lord</hi> can ſoone tread him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſlime. But (perhaps) he will offer him heapes of <hi>Coyne,</hi> and thinke to buy out his <hi>Sinne</hi> with <hi>Siluer.</hi> No: <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Siluer</hi> are <hi>corruptible things,</hi> and the <hi>Samuel</hi> of <hi>Heauen</hi> will take no Bribes. Now how <hi>rare</hi> this <hi>Faith</hi> is (howſoeuer the <hi>World</hi> thinkes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more common) the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> in his
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20993:8"/> 
               <hi>Combat,</hi> findes by experience. Before hee commit <hi>ſinne,</hi> the <hi>Serpent</hi> tels him, hee ſhall not dye at all; and, come what will come, it is but <hi>Beleeuing in Chriſt:</hi> but when he hath yeelded to the temptation, then he ſhewes him <hi>Halters,</hi> and <hi>Kniues,</hi> and <hi>Poyſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus (no doubt) the <hi>Deuill</hi> inſulted ouer <hi>Dauid,</hi> when he was in penning the <hi>one</hi> and <hi>fifteeth Pſalme.</hi> VVhy, how now <hi>Dauid,</hi> are you fallen to a <hi>Pſalme</hi> of <hi>Mercy?</hi> Are you at laſt come to whyning and puling for your ſinnes? O, <hi>Sir,</hi> you ſhould haue lookt better about you: it is now too late to call againe yeſterday. Thou arrant <hi>Hypocrite,</hi> how dar'ſt thou lift vp thoſe eyes, thoſe <hi>adulterous</hi> eyes to Heauen? How dar'ſt thou ſpread thoſe hands, thoſe <hi>murtherous</hi> hands before the <hi>Lord?</hi> VVhat? the <hi>King?</hi> the <hi>King of Iſrael?</hi> a <hi>Prophet?</hi> and play the <hi>Beaſt?</hi> Is your <hi>Zeale</hi> and <hi>Dancing before the Arke</hi> come to this? And would no leſſe <hi>ſinne</hi> ſerue thy turne than <hi>Adulterie?</hi> Could not thine owne wife, nay wiues ſuffice thee? Is the breach of holy <hi>Matrimony</hi> nothing? No,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20993:8"/> no, it was nothing, and therefore to make it ſomething, thou laſheſt into <hi>murther,</hi> and chaineſt thy <hi>ſinnes</hi> together. But, if thou wilt needes kill, I hope it ſhall be ſome <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtine.</hi> Calſt thou <hi>Vriah</hi> a <hi>Philiſtine?</hi> Thou <hi>Tyrant,</hi> thine owne Conſcience tels thee, it was thy <hi>Subiect,</hi> thy faithfull, honeſt, and valiant <hi>Subiect,</hi> whom craftily thou caldſt home, and all to hatch thy <hi>Cuckowes-egg,</hi> by<note place="margin">2 Sam. 11. 13.</note> ſame token thou mad'ſt him <hi>drunke,</hi> and thou neuer the better, and hee much the worſe. Ah Sir, who would haue thought that <hi>Dauid</hi> could play ſuch pranckes? Thy other <hi>ſinnes</hi> I haue vpon <hi>Record,</hi> and they be forth-comming, but theſe will I write in a <hi>paper by themſelues in Text-letters,</hi> and pinne them on the <hi>Curtaine</hi> at thy <hi>Beds-feet,</hi> when thou lieſt a dying. And ſo farewell for a ſeaſon.</p>
            <p>I proceede to this <hi>Womans liberall Intent.</hi> She goes not empty-handed, but takes with her a <hi>Boxe of Oyntment,</hi> with full purpoſe to beſtow it on <hi>Chriſt.</hi> The <hi>Boxe</hi> is <hi>Alabaſter,</hi> ſo called of <hi>A,</hi> the <hi>priuatiue particle,</hi> and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20993:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>hard to be held for the ſlippirineſſe.</hi> A fit Veſſell for ſuch piercing <hi>aeriall</hi> matter. The <hi>Oyntment</hi> was not <hi>groſſe</hi> and <hi>ſophiſticate,</hi> but pure and coſtly, being (to ſpeake in the <hi>Schoole-mens</hi> phraſe) <hi>Refrigerativum, Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitivum, Confortativum, Cooling, Suppling, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing,</hi> chiefly with the <hi>odour,</hi> which was like the ſweet ſent of <hi>Muske, Ciuet, Amber-Greece.</hi> This was her <hi>Preſent</hi> reſolu'd vpon for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> not in opinion of <hi>Merit</hi> (for that were to proffer him the <hi>Nard,</hi> and to throw the <hi>Alabaſter</hi> at his head) but in token of the <hi>ſoundneſſe of her Faith,</hi> the <hi>truth of her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion,</hi> and the <hi>dearneſſe of her affection to him,</hi> who had already giuen her <hi>hanſell</hi> of his abundant mercies. A notable <hi>Patterne</hi> and <hi>Platforme</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianitie,</hi> declaring that good thoughts muſt be nouriſhed by <hi>conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance,</hi> fortified by <hi>Prayer,</hi> and not iuſtled out by <hi>rouing cogitations.</hi> For a <hi>diuine motion</hi> kild ſoone after the <hi>conception,</hi> is like an <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brio,</hi> vnkindly periſhing in the wombe. But that we may build on a ſure foundation, we muſt looke that our purpoſes haue ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20993:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Originals, Directions, Ends,</hi> ſince <hi>Aduerbs</hi> in <hi>Scripture,</hi> are more <hi>forcible</hi> than <hi>Nownes,</hi> and <hi>Benè</hi> better than <hi>Bonum.</hi> This churliſh <hi>age</hi> admits no thought of <hi>Spiknard</hi> for <hi>Chriſt.</hi> VVhat, nothing to carry him? <hi>Nothing.</hi> VVhats the cauſe? VVant. True, want of <hi>Deuotion.</hi> For otherwiſe the <hi>pooreſt</hi> man hath two <hi>Mites</hi> to giue him, his <hi>Soule</hi> and his <hi>Body.</hi> But paſſe wee on to this <hi>Chriſtian</hi> womans <hi>Humilitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shee ſtood,</hi> that is, <hi>ſhe remayned at his feet,</hi> for ſo <hi>ſtanding</hi> is taken in the <hi>ſeuenth</hi> of the <hi>Acts,</hi> the 55. <hi>verſe,</hi> and in other places. The <hi>Foote</hi> is the loweſt part of the body, and is oppoſed to the <hi>Head,</hi> the principall member for <hi>Order, Perfection, Vertue.</hi> This ſilly wretch is here ſtooping to the ground; in abaſement of her ſelfe for her grieuous of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences: for <hi>Humilitie</hi> thinkes nothing more ſtrange, and incredible, than the report or <hi>ſuppoſall</hi> of her owne worthineſſe. A vertue ſo honourable, that <hi>Pride</hi> (her enemy) vvill ſtriue to reſemble her. The <hi>Virgin Mary</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>) was adorned with <hi>three</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:20993:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> flowers, the <hi>Violet,</hi> the <hi>Lilly,</hi> the <hi>Roſe,</hi> with <hi>Humilitie, Chaſtitie, Charitie.</hi> And, in truth, all <hi>Graces</hi> looſe their gloſſe and brightnes, goe not <hi>Humilitie</hi> before them, beſide them, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them. Downe then, <hi>proud heart,</hi> that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer yet felſt the weight of <hi>Sinne,</hi> the wrath of GOD, the wound of <hi>Conſcience:</hi> downe on thy knees, this day, this night, leaſt thou be in thy winding-ſheet, in thy graue, &amp; in the fire of <hi>Hell</hi> by to morrow. Say vnto the Lord, in the anguiſh of thy ſoule, Lord, I am a wretched, &amp; wofull creature, I am nothing but <hi>ſinne. Sin</hi> in the wombe, <hi>ſinne</hi> in the birth, <hi>ſinne in the</hi> cradle, <hi>ſinne</hi> in my youth, <hi>ſinne</hi> in my riper age; blinde in iudgement, dull in memory, ſtubborne in hart, wayward in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, vain in words, peruerſe in manners; an outragious Swearer, a damnable <hi>Mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preacher,</hi> a curſed <hi>Sabbaoth-breaker,</hi> a <hi>Theefe,</hi> a <hi>Barabbas,</hi> a <hi>Viper,</hi> a <hi>Carrion,</hi> ah <hi>Lord,</hi> ſo loathſome, and ſo full of poyſon, that I know not how to expreſſe my vileneſſe.</p>
            <p>There followeth the <hi>Modeſty</hi> of this <hi>Saint. She ſtood behinde him.</hi> Shee dare not preſume
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20993:10"/> to behold his countenance, but (like the <hi>wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man with the bloudy Iſſue</hi>) comes ſtealing <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde</hi>
               <note place="margin">Marke 5. 27.</note> 
               <hi>him,</hi> with a trembling hart, and bluſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hue (the colour of vertue.) And here (as euery where) behold a wonderfull alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. She had beene wilde, and audacious, giuing her members <hi>ſeruants to vncleannes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6. 19.</note> dallying with her hands, minſing with her feete, ſmiling with her cheekes, glancing with her eyes, flaring with her haire, kiſſing vvith her lips, impudent in all, and all to make others impudent: but now ſhe is aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of her ſelfe, and creepes at the backe of this noble <hi>Gueſt,</hi> with eyes ſo demiſſe, &amp; geſture ſo modeſtly compoſed, as if <hi>Baſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes</hi> it ſelfe were confined to her <hi>perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then, let vs here caſt our eyes on this <hi>Shamefaſtnes:</hi> a <hi>paſsion,</hi> in <hi>yong-men</hi> commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, in <hi>women</hi> admirable, which <hi>good men</hi> neede not, but by accident, which <hi>old men</hi> would not haue, which <hi>bad men</hi> cannot haue. I will ſhew you (if you pleaſe) her <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture,</hi> drawne by a cunning hand, aboue <hi>foure hundred yeeres agoe,</hi> and the <hi>Table</hi> yet
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20993:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſound, and the <hi>colours</hi> freſh. She is <hi>the Siſter</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard. ad Mil. Temp.</note> 
               <hi>of Continencie, the Diſcouerer of Simplicitie, the Lampe of Chaſtitie, the Defender of Puritie, Conſciences Glory, Fames Keeper, Lifes Honor, Vertues Seate, Natures Praiſe, Honeſties Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance.</hi> Yet as <hi>louely</hi> as <hi>ſhe</hi> is, <hi>ſhe</hi> is little ſet by in this <hi>ſenſuall</hi> age, which ſpending it ſelfe in bruitiſh pleaſure, hath a face of Braſſe, though <hi>Shame,</hi> by <hi>Nature,</hi> be intail'd to <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperance,</hi> as a vice moſt repugnant to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane excellencie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Deſire</hi> now haſten vs forward to this womans <hi>godly Sorrow,</hi> vvhich ſhe teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies by <hi>teares,</hi> the <hi>dew of Grace,</hi> the <hi>ioy of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</hi> The <hi>Compunction</hi> of the wicked is ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Ceremoniall</hi> or <hi>Deſperate:</hi> from vvhich this differs, both in the <hi>forme,</hi> as being a <hi>true griefe,</hi> allayed by the comforts of the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell:</hi> and in the <hi>effect,</hi> as comming to GOD, when the other flyes from him. The <hi>Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants</hi> of it are <hi>ſeauen: Care, Apologie, Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Feare, Vehement Deſire, Zeale, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge.</hi> The <hi>Parts</hi> are <hi>three, Diſcuſsion, Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, Deteſtation:</hi> by the <hi>firſt</hi> vvee make
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20993:11"/> priuie-ſearch for our ſinnes: by the <hi>ſecond,</hi> we put them in hold: by the <hi>third,</hi> vve cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure them with bitternes and adiudge them to death. The <hi>Meanes</hi> of it are <hi>eight; The Knowledge of the Law, of the Sanctions of the Law, of the Contempt of both, of the Guilt of ſinne, of the Judgement of God againſt it, of the Price of our Ranſome, of the End of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption,</hi> and <hi>of the Promiſe of Saluation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now all this Knowledge, and (by ſequel) this <hi>Sorrow,</hi> is from God, chiefly wrought by ſharp (but diſcreet) <hi>Application of the word.</hi> This is that <hi>Ieſus</hi> vvhom <hi>Yee</hi> haue cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,<note place="margin">Acts 2. 36.</note> ſaith <hi>Peter</hi> to the <hi>Iewes: He</hi> ſets the <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> in the right place, this <hi>yee,</hi> was it that <hi>prickt</hi> them to the hearts. Yet muſt vve take heed vve throw not ſtones at the head of <hi>Innocencie,</hi> nor vent our <hi>gall</hi> to the <hi>diſgrace</hi> of <hi>Perſons.</hi> But, Oh, for a <hi>Moſes</hi> in theſe dayes, to fetch <hi>water</hi> from the <hi>Rocke,</hi> and <hi>tears</hi> from the eies of our hard-harted <hi>drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards,</hi> who ſwarme in euery place, carow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>mans-bloud</hi> in Cans, and Flagons. The land, at this day, <hi>mourneth</hi> becauſe of <hi>Oaths.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 23. 10.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:20993:12"/>
            <p>From the <hi>Noble-man</hi> to the <hi>Kitchin-boy,</hi> and from the <hi>Lady</hi> to the <hi>Inckle-begger,</hi> there is nothing but <hi>Swearing.</hi> They champe in their mouthes <hi>the bloud of</hi> GOD, as <hi>Paul</hi> calls it: that bloud, that <hi>ſpeaketh better things than that of Abel,</hi> the leaſt droppe whereof is<note place="margin">Actes 20. 28. Hebr. 12. 24.</note> more worth than <hi>Mines</hi> of <hi>precious Mettall,</hi> nay Gold, and Siluer are but <hi>Tinker-mettall</hi> to it. VVould you know the chiefe cauſe of this enormity? It's want of <hi>application:</hi> which once ſet on foote, would ſmite the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of theſe offenders, and ſting the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate</hi> for his cruell pitty, and dangerous conniuencie. But now, ſince the <hi>Preacher</hi> acts the <hi>Paraſites</hi> part (fearing the <hi>ſpeech</hi> of <hi>Ahab</hi> to <hi>Michajah,</hi> the ſame, in effect, with <hi>Agamemnons</hi> to <hi>Calchas,</hi>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <note place="margin">Hom. Il. 1.</note>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <hi>Did I not tell you, he would not propheſie good, but euill?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Kin. 22. 18.</note>
               </q> ſince then hath <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> tane head, and feeling the reines lie looſe, hath layd Gods honor in the duſt. Ad to this euil, the laſines of our <hi>vnlearned Ministers,</hi> who are all the ſixe daies meerely <hi>ſecular,</hi> and ſo but read, if
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20993:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> reade on the ſeauenth.</p>
            <p>The next point contiguous to this, is <hi>the Increaſe of this womans godly ſorrow.</hi> VVhen the body receiues a wound, at firſt you ſee nothing but a <hi>white line:</hi> forthwith comes out bloud in great abundance. Deep griefe for ſinne is a while inteſtate, at laſt it yeelds <hi>teares,</hi> more ſparingly at firſt, but after <hi>plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly.</hi> Thus <hi>Eliahs</hi> Cloud vvas but like a<note place="margin">1 Kin. 18.</note> 
               <hi>mans hand</hi> at the riſing, preſently the <hi>heauen</hi> vvas <hi>blacke,</hi> and there vvas a <hi>great rayne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>meaſure</hi> of this <hi>griefe</hi> muſt be <hi>great,</hi> &amp; <hi>ſerious;</hi> yet can it not poſſibly be <hi>propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall</hi> to the <hi>ſinne,</hi> as <hi>Scotus</hi> dreames: which <hi>Bellarmin</hi> qualifying by the <hi>distinction</hi> of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſiue,</hi> &amp; <hi>Appreciatiue,</hi> though he gather vp his feet more cleanly than the <hi>Schoole-man,</hi> yet is he found to inter-fere in his pace.</p>
            <p>That we may conceiue great <hi>griefe,</hi> wee muſt acknowledge our ſelues <hi>great ſinners,</hi> and beware of the <hi>Negation, Extenuation, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification</hi> of our offences: for though we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer committed heinous crime to the world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, yet many ſmall <hi>ſins</hi> clotterd together,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20993:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> will make a ſad <hi>lumpe:</hi> though in truth no ſinne be <hi>little</hi> in it ſelfe, but <hi>damnable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Romanists</hi> make but <hi>ſeauen Deadly ſinnes,</hi> all which are couched in this word <hi>SALIGIA.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vt mortem vites, ſemper</hi> SALIGIA <hi>vites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>S,</hi> is meant <hi>Superbia,</hi> by <hi>A, Avaritia,</hi> by <hi>L, Luxuria,</hi> by <hi>I, Ira,</hi> by <hi>G, Gula,</hi> by <hi>I, Invidia,</hi> by <hi>A, Accidia,</hi> or rather <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Crafty <hi>Cubs;</hi> for they haue left out <hi>Idolatry</hi> that <hi>Maſter-ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Foure things declare the <hi>grieuouſneſſe</hi> of <hi>ſinne; The Law; Puniſhment in our ſelues and others; Terror of conſcience; The death of Christ.</hi> There are <hi>foure Crying ſinnes,</hi> for which wee muſt weepe, like <hi>Rahel,</hi> that would not be comforted: <hi>Murder, Sodomitrie, Oppreſsion of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Geneſ. 4. 10. Geneſ. 19. 13. Exo. 22. 23. Iames 3. 4.</note> 
               <hi>widows and Orphanes, and Detayning of wages.</hi> Some of theſe <hi>ſinnes</hi> are rife among vs; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God calls vs to <hi>baldnes,</hi> and <hi>ſack-cloth:</hi> but behold <hi>Ioy</hi> and <hi>Gladneſſe, ſlaying Oxen, and killing Sheepe, eating Fleſh, and drinking</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſaiah 22. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Wine.</hi> Nay we haue learn'd the <hi>Epicures En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thymeme, The Prophet Eſay</hi> ſaies, <hi>We must die tomorrow; Therefore let vs eate and drinke.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:20993:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>In the next place let vs view this womans <hi>Neglect of her ſelfe: She wipes Christs feet with the haires of her head.</hi> Certainely <hi>ſhe</hi> wanted not <hi>fine linnen</hi> to haue dride them, but now ſhee will conſecrate her deereſt <hi>Ornament,</hi> which ſo oft, which ſo gently ſhee had kemb'd, and broyded ſo cunningly againſt the Glaſſe. The <hi>haire</hi> is but a poore <hi>Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> yet ſtrange it is how ſome admire it. The <hi>Callant</hi> muſt haue his <hi>fleece</hi> of <hi>Vanitie,</hi> at leaſt, one <hi>Locke</hi> effeminately twiſted. For which <hi>pride,</hi> hee is ſometime ſo iuſtly pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht, that hee's forc't to fall to his <hi>Gregori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</hi> Our <hi>Daughters</hi> of <hi>Sion,</hi> ſpend the <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning-time</hi> (the <hi>prime</hi> and freſheſt of the day, and fitteſt for <hi>Prayer</hi>) in criſping, curling, building Towers on their heads: changing the colour with liquors, powders: borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and buying, of the liuing, of the dead. Nay, they counterfait the <hi>great Seale of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and walke with artificiall Complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which GOD will one day waſh off with <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>brimstone,</hi> fall they not in time to <hi>Deprecation.</hi> Thus wethreaten, but what
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20993:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> care they? They will ſhrieke, and ſqueale, at the leaping of a <hi>frogge,</hi> but not ſhrinke an inch for all the curſes in the <hi>Bible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVe are now to conſider this womans <hi>loue: She kiſſed his feete. Fiue</hi> kindes of <hi>Kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> are found in <hi>Scripture.</hi> The <hi>firſt</hi> a <hi>whoriſh one: ſo ſhee caught him, and kiſſed him, Prou.</hi> 7. 13. The <hi>ſecond a chaste one:</hi> thus <hi>Iacob kiſſed</hi> his cozen <hi>Rahel, Ge.</hi> 29. 11. The <hi>third the Kiſſe</hi> of <hi>Curteſie: Thou gauest me no Kiſſe, Luke</hi> 7. 45. The <hi>fourth the Kiſſe of Treaſon:</hi> Thus <hi>Ioab kist Amaſa, 2. Sam.</hi> 20: and <hi>Iſcariot</hi> our <hi>Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, Matth.</hi> 26. 49. The <hi>fift, the Symbole</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> and <hi>Brother-hood; Greete one another with an holy Kiſſe, 2 Corin.</hi> 13. 12. This <hi>Kiſſe</hi> was <hi>reuerent,</hi> and argu'd the <hi>truth</hi> of <hi>Loue,</hi> which <hi>Loue</hi> (to vſe <hi>Scaligers definition</hi>) is <hi>an affection vniting the ſoule with Christ.</hi> It im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports <hi>three</hi> things, an <hi>Inclination,</hi> wherewith ſhee was affected: a <hi>Deſire,</hi> wherewith ſhee was rauiſhed: a <hi>Ioy,</hi> wherewith ſhee was quieted. The <hi>meaſure</hi> of this <hi>Loue is without meaſure,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard.</hi> The <hi>Schoole-men</hi> giue two acute <hi>Reaſons.</hi> Firſt, becauſe <hi>Loue</hi> is the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20993:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> vtmoſt end of our affections. Now the <hi>End</hi> of <hi>Deſire</hi> is without <hi>End.</hi> Therefore the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian</hi> puts an <hi>end</hi> to his <hi>medicine,</hi> neuer to<note place="margin">Ariſs. Pol. 1.</note> the <hi>health</hi> of his <hi>Patient.</hi> Secondly, a <hi>meaſure</hi> is found in <hi>Loue,</hi> not as in the <hi>thing meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> but as in the <hi>meaſure,</hi> in which there can be no <hi>exceſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Aduerſaries, that call themſelues <hi>Catholiques</hi> (as did the <hi>Arrians</hi> and <hi>Donatists</hi>) avouch with confidence, that they onely <hi>loue Christ.</hi> How proue they it? By an <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument</hi> drawne from <hi>Kiſsing:</hi> they <hi>Kiſſe</hi> his <hi>Picture,</hi> the <hi>Pax,</hi> the <hi>Altar.</hi> But ſtay: the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites,</hi> vnder <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> might ſtand as much on ſuch <hi>kiſsing</hi> as they: yet the Prophet <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſea</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſea 13. 2.</note> tells them they <hi>kist</hi> the <hi>Calues.</hi> Do our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 17.</note> diſſolute <hi>Catholikes</hi> loue <hi>God?</hi> Then would they loue our dread <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> his <hi>Vicegerent.</hi> So they doe: ſo they ſay.</p>
            <p>No, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> (their <hi>Pythagoras</hi>) reades them another <hi>Leſſon, De Rom. Pont. lib. 5. c, 7. Non licet Christianis tolerare Regem Haereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum: It's not lawfull for Christians to indure a King that's an Heretique.</hi> And what <hi>King</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:20993:15"/> counts hee an <hi>Heretique?</hi> The <hi>Protestant.</hi> VVitnes his owne words: <hi>Regnante Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tino, florebat fides Christiana. When Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine raigned, there was nothing but Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme: When Constantius raigned, there was nothing but Arrianiſme: VVhen Iulian reigned, there was nothing but Ethniciſme: VVhen</hi> Henry <hi>of England, and</hi> Edward <hi>reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, there was nothing but Lutheriſme: VVhen</hi> Elizabeth <hi>reigned, there was nothing but Caluiniſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now when <hi>Subiects</hi> are thus <hi>Ieſuited</hi> (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe GOD reſtraine them) they ſtudy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly the <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>King-killing.</hi> Shooting as dead as <hi>Maureuell,</hi> poyſoning as ſure as <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zuto,</hi> ſtabbing as right as the <hi>Iacobin,</hi> goring as deepe as <hi>Ravilack.</hi> VVhen firſt I beheld the <hi>Quarters</hi> of the <hi>Pouder-traitors,</hi> my heart began to earne, and the teares ſtood in mine eies: at laſt, I was ſorie that I was ſorie, and charg'd my ſoule not to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>paſsion.</hi> O! but they will neuer do ſo more: Not till the next time: For at this houre (like <hi>Catilins</hi>) they <hi>note vs with their eyes,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20993:15"/> and deſigne vs euery one to Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At laſt we are almoſt come a-ſhoare, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to caſt <hi>Anchor;</hi> for now remayneth one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this womans <hi>Bountie</hi> to be touched. Shee <hi>annoynteth Chriſts feet with Oyntment.</hi> The <hi>annoynting</hi> the head, was an act of <hi>kindneſſe,</hi> much vſed <hi>then</hi> at <hi>Bankets,</hi> in the <hi>Eaſt-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries:</hi> for vs we muſt ſhow from this <hi>Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> the life of our <hi>Faith,</hi> by <hi>Communicatiue</hi> goodneſſe. And this muſt be performed <hi>ſincerely,</hi> that the <hi>Neighbour-hand</hi> take not notice of the deed: <hi>chearfully,</hi> that the eye be not clouded with diſdaine: <hi>ſeaſonably,</hi> that the heart be not broken with delay: <hi>plente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly,</hi> that <hi>all</hi> may haue ſome: <hi>diſcreetly,</hi> that ſome may not haue <hi>all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rich man;</hi> thou ſhalt periſh ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, though thou neuer <hi>hurt</hi> the <hi>poore,</hi> if thou doe not <hi>helpe</hi> them. <hi>Depart from me yee curſed into euerlaſting fire</hi> (ſaith our <hi>Sauiour:</hi>) for what? for <hi>Oppreſsing</hi> the <hi>Needy?</hi> and for <hi>ſinnes</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 25. 41. 24</note> of <hi>Commiſsion?</hi> No, for not <hi>Succouring</hi> the <hi>Needy,</hi> and for <hi>ſinnes</hi> of <hi>Omiſsion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVhat then will become of the <hi>ſacrilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:20993:16"/> Patron,</hi> that <hi>Rob-God?</hi> (I'le not eate the word, for I had it from the <hi>Prophet Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy:</hi>) hee thinkes the <hi>Tenth</hi> a <hi>golden Fleece,</hi> and a <hi>goodly Sheafe,</hi> but hee ſhall finde that the <hi>lockes</hi> of the one, and the <hi>yawnes</hi> of the other, ſhall choke him. Shortly will the <hi>Lord</hi> ariſe, lay himſelfe fayre in his <hi>Bow,</hi> and ſend the <hi>Arrowes</hi> of <hi>Death</hi> ſinging into his boſome.</p>
            <p>And what will become of the <hi>Lord of the Towne,</hi> that takes away the <hi>Commons,</hi> incloſes whole <hi>fields,</hi> vnpeoples the <hi>Country,</hi> rackes, improues, vndoes his <hi>Tenants,</hi> kils the <hi>Dam</hi> with the <hi>young-ones,</hi> the <hi>Mother</hi> with the <hi>Children?</hi> Let him <hi>reſtore,</hi> and doe the <hi>workes of Mercy</hi> quickely, or, as the <hi>Lord</hi> liues, he ſhall wring his hands, and rue the time that euer hee was borne.</p>
            <p>And what will become of the brauing <hi>Knight,</hi> that builds like <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> drinkes like <hi>Tyberius,</hi> ſpends all, more than all, in <hi>Reuils,</hi> in <hi>Licentiouſneſſe?</hi> His <hi>Chimnies</hi> ſhall cry <hi>vengeance</hi> againſt him, that breathe out no reliefe to the <hi>Orphan,</hi> hee ſhall ſigh out a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20993:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Tandem ſi,</hi> and griefe ſhall breake the kall of his heart.</p>
            <p>And what will become of the grim <hi>Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer?</hi> O wretch! yet will he tell you, ſome <hi>Miniſters</hi> approue him, yea, and ioyne with him in the <hi>Trade. O Theife! O Theeues!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what will become of the vnconſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable <hi>Lawyer,</hi> that leades his <hi>Clyent</hi> into a <hi>Maze</hi> of <hi>trouble?</hi> A <hi>Motion</hi> to day, to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row croſt, <hi>Execution</hi> ſuſpended, and cald in queſtion by a <hi>Writ of Errour.</hi> I hope, ſayes the plodding weather-beaten <hi>Soule,</hi> I ſhall haue an end of my <hi>Sute</hi> the <hi>next Tearme.</hi> Nay, nor the <hi>next Tearme,</hi> nor the <hi>next;</hi> nay, nor the <hi>next</hi> yeere, nor the <hi>next.</hi> Behold, the <hi>Lord</hi> will be a <hi>Lion</hi> to theſe men, as he vvas to <hi>Iudah;</hi> or elſe a <hi>Moth,</hi> as he was to <hi>Iſrael:</hi> he will eyther deſtroy them ſodainely, or conſume them lingringly.</p>
            <p>And what will become of the <hi>ſlye Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheriffe,</hi> who will take <hi>double fees,</hi> that <hi>Gry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin-like</hi> he may <hi>floore</hi> his <hi>Neſt</hi> with <hi>Gold?</hi> Doubtleſſe this <hi>ſinne</hi> is written with a <hi>Pen</hi> of <hi>Iron,</hi> and with the <hi>Claw</hi> of a <hi>Diamond.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:20993:17"/>
            <p>And what will become of our <hi>Lamb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bayliues,</hi> and <hi>Cheeſe-bayliues,</hi> who to ſtocke their ground, and cram their wallet, vvill let <hi>honeſt</hi> men alone, when the <hi>Sediment</hi> of the <hi>Country</hi> muſt be ſtird vp for <hi>Iurers?</hi> Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theſe things are in the eares of the Lord of <hi>Hoſts,</hi> the <hi>Author,</hi> and <hi>Patron</hi> of <hi>Iuſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If now ſome <hi>Sycophant</hi> ſhall cloſely ſay, Hee's bold with others, but dare not come neare the <hi>Scarlet-Robes:</hi> let him take this <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere</hi> from him, who was neuer yet taxt for ſoothing greatneſſe: <hi>This Circuit neuer ſaw</hi>
               <note place="margin">The L. Chiefe Iuſtice of England, and I. Winch.</note> 
               <hi>ſo Reuerend Iudges.</hi> For which mercy, and all other, to GOD, the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Sonne,</hi> and the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> be <hi>honor</hi> and <hi>glory,</hi> for euer and euer.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20993:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
